<section xml:id="game-categories">
    <title>Organizing the World of Games</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn that games can be organized into many different groups based on how the games are
                    played.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn the difference between games of perfect and imperfect information.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn the difference between symmetric and asymmetric games.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn how to play Nim.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <observation>
        What types of genres of games do you enjoy? What do you enjoy about them?
    </observation>

    <p>
        One of the major goals of mathematical thinking is the ability to organize objects into groups based on their
        properties. The first layer of this is determine whether something is a game. But once we have a game, there
        are many additional ways to continue to try to categorize it.
    </p>
    <p>
        One of the first ways you might think of organizing a game is based on the number of players. Chess is a game
        played by two players. Board games commonly accommodate two to four players. And a game like Sudoku is a
        single player game. 
    </p>
    <p>
        We can also consider whether a game includes an element of chance or does not. Chance is introduced into a game
        any time there is some type of randomizing element. This can be in the form of rolling dice, spinning a wheel,
        or drawing cards. In some contexts, it can be helpful to imagine that chance is just another player in the game.
        For example, instead of rolling a die, you can imagine that the player "chance" is simply selecting a number
        from 1 to 6. But for our purposes, we will hold the view that is part of the game and not a player.
    </p>
    <p>
        Another property of a game is whether the there is information that is hidden from some or all of the players.
        For example, one of the reasons poker is interesting is because the each player has their own cards that nobody
        else can see, and one of the challenges is to try to figure out what cards the other players might be holding
        based on how they are behaving. In a game like Monopoly, there is a stack of cards (Chance or Community Chest)
        and the players aren't allowed to peek at them in advance. This means that when a player lands on one of those
        positions, information that was hidden becomes revealed to all of the players. Another way that information can
        be hidden is when there is an element of chance. An outcome may depend on which number is rolled, and none of
        the players have access to that information. The opposite of this is a gmae where all the information is in
        front of the players from the very beginning. The games of chess and checker are examples of this. There is no
        part of the game that his hidden from the players. We have special terms for these game types.
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-perfect-imperfect">
        <title>Games with Perfect and Imperfect Information</title>
        <idx><h>perfect</h></idx>
        <idx><h>imperfect</h></idx>
        <idx><h>incomplete</h></idx>
        <idx><h>complete</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A game with <term>perfect</term> information is a game in which all the players have access to all of
                the information in a game. A game with <term>imperfect</term> information is a game in which at least
                one of the players does not have access to all of the information in a game. This includes players not
                knowing the outcome of future chance events. Some people use the terms <term>complete</term> and
                <term>incomplete</term> information instead of perfect and imperfect information, respectively.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        Most people are familiar with games in each of the above categories, as the typical types of games that people
        play include games on both sides of the line for each of the divisions. But there are still more ways to
        categorize games. These categories are generally intuitive to understand, but it may be harder to think of
        examples.
    </p>
    <p>
        Games can be either competitive or cooperative. A cooperative game is one where all of the players win or lose
        as a single team. There are plenty of examples of these types of games, but they are likely less familiar to
        the average person. Instead, most people are able to think of competitive games. These are games where, at the
        end of the game, some players win and some players lose. It's important to note that competitive games may
        involve some elements of cooperation, where you might develop temporary alliances because you can attain some
        sort of benefit from it.
    </p>
    <p>
        A more abstract way of looking at games is to consider the possible moves for each player. In some games, each
        player has their own pieces that they control, and so each player has a different set of possible moves at any
        given moment in the game. But there are some games in which all players have the exact same possible decisions
        all the time. We will start with the formal definition.
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-symmetric-asymmetric">
        <title>Symmetric and Asymmetric Games</title>
        <idx><h>symmetric (game)</h></idx>
        <idx><h>asymmetric (game)</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>symmetric</term> game is a game for which both players have identical options at any decision
                point during the game. An <term>asymmetric</term> game is a game where one player has an option
                available to them that the other player (or players) do not.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        Any game where each player has their own pieces to move is an asymmetric game. For example, chess is an
        asymmetric game. The word "identical" in this definition is a key point to focus on. Even though chess starts
        off with the pieces in a mirror image of each other, and both players move their corresponding pieces in the
        same way, that's not what is meant by identical. When it's white's turn, they can move a white pawn in a certain
        way. But if it were black's turn, they would not be able to move that same white pawn in the same way. They are
        forbidden from moving any of white's pieces at all! So when you think about identical moves, you want to think
        of it as literally being able to do the exact same thing in the exact same way.
    </p>
    <p>    
        A symmetric game that you might know is called "Nim." This is an example of a heap game, which is just a general
        term for games that are played with tokens that are put into piles (heaps), and the gmae is played by
        manipulating those heaps. These games are convenient because they can be played with objects that are just lying
        around. Examples of convenient tokens are coins, beans, or small stones. We will explain the rules of the game
        and then discuss why it's a symmetric game.
    </p>

    <fact xml:id="game-nim">
        <title>Nim</title>
        <idx><h>nim</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                Nim is two-player heap game. Players take turns selecting a heap and removing any number of tokens from
                it. The player who takes the last token from the last remaining heap is the winner.
            </p>
            <p>
                A common starting arrangement is to have one heap of size three, one heap of size five, and one heap of
                size seven. However, the game can start with any number of heaps with any number of tokens in them.
            </p>
        </statement>
        <figure xml:id="video-nim">
            <title>Nim Video Instructions</title>
            <video youtube="eM3S74kchoM">
            </video>
            <caption>Video instructions for Nim</caption>
        </figure>
    </fact>

    <p>
        This is a symmetric game because both players have access to the exact same moves from any position. There is no
        sense in which one player has their own heaps that the other player can't take from. All the heaps are neutral
        and when it's each player's turn they have the same rules for how they can make their next move.
    </p>

    <p>
        We will close this section by introducting a useful concept for talking about games.
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-game-state">
        <title>Game State</title>
        <idx><h>game state</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                At any instant for any game, the <term>game state</term> is the collection of all of the information
                necessary to describe the current game decision point.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        For Nim, the game state is the list of all of the heaps with the number of tokens in each heap. We do not need
        to know whose turn it is because the game is symmetric. The available decisions for either player is the same.
        For checkers, the game state is the position of every checker on the board and which color is next to move. We
        need to know whose turn it is because that tells us which pieces are available to be moved.
    </p>
    <p>
        Thinking about game states will be useful for us as we start to analyze games. It's important to note that the
        game state does not necessarily contain the information about how you got to that point. For example, the game
        state for Nim might be that there is only one heap with three tokens in it. We have no idea what combination of
        moves actually got us to this position. It turns out that (at least for this game) how you got to a position is
        irrelevant for how you strategize moving forward.
    </p>

    <worksheet xml:id="game-categories-wksht">
		<title>Exercises</title>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>Identifying Features of Games</title>
            <p>
                For each of the following games, identify the following features:
                <ul>
                    <li>
                        <p>The number of players (it may be a range of numbers)</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Whether it is a game with or without chance</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Whether it is a game with complete or incomplete information</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Whether it is a cooperative or competitive game</p>
                    </li>
                    <li>
                        <p>Whether it is a symmetric or asymmetric game</p>
                    </li>
                </ul>
            </p>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Chess
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Poker
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Scrabble
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Nim
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Monopoly
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>Exploring Nim</title>
            <p>
                Later in the course, we are going to learn some formal techniques for analyzing games. But for now, we
                will simply use intuition and experience to analyze the game (tools that everyone has access to).
            </p>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Suppose that it's your turn, and there is only one heap with four tokens in it. What is your best
                    play and why? Can you generalize from this situation and come up with a strategy for similar
                    sitations?
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Suppose that it's your turn, and there are two heaps remaining. One heap has 4 tokens and the other
                    heap has just 1 token. What is your play and why? Can you generalize from this situation and come
                    up with a strategy for similar situations? 
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </worksheet>

</section>