<section xml:id="game-intro">
    <title>A Simple Question with a Complicated Answer</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn to defininition of a game for the purposes of this course.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn how to determine whether an activity is a game for the purposes of this course.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <observation>
        Make a list of games that you've played. Are there any common features about the items in your list? Do these
        features apply to all games? If not, what features do you believe are shared by all games?
    </observation>

    <p>
        What is a game? Since everyone has some experience playing games, it's not hard to think of examples of games.
        Some people might think of board games (chess, Monopoly, and Settler's of Catan are just a few examples). Some
        people might think of first-person shooters like Call of Duty, or any number of console games that can be found
        on the Nintendo Switch or XBox. There are also games involving cards like poker and Blackjack.
    </p>
    <p>
        But then there's also a gray area. Is a jigsaw puzzle a game? What about logic puzzles and Sudoku? Or what about
        playing "Peek-A-Boo" with a baby? As you think about it longer, the boundary between what is a game and what is
        not a game starts to get fuzzy.
    </p>
    <p>
        And this leads us back to the question: What is a game? We're not going to try to come up with a definition that
        defines all possible games. That type of categorization can be interesting, but it can also lead to endless
        debates that distract from the larger ideas. The real purpose of this definition is to set the stage for this
        course. When we talk about a game in this course, we are only talking about certain types of games and not all
        possible games. So with that in mind, here is the definition. 
    </p>
    <aside>
        <p>
            Trying to make universal definitions can lead to debates such as whether a hot dog is a sandwich or whether
            cereal is a soup.
        </p>
    </aside>

    <definition xml:id="def-game">
        <title>Game</title>
        <idx><h>game</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>game</term> is an activity with a set of well-defined rules, well-defined decision points, and
                well-defined outcomes.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>

    <p>
        Mathematicians use the term "well-defined" in formal mathematical contexts to mean that the idea or object can
        be determined unambiguously. In other words, it can be determined in a manner that everyone can look at it and
        agree on what it is. The use of that term here is (unfortunately) not quite as precise, as there is still some
        wiggle room for the concepts. However, for this course, it's close enough. We will elaborate on the ideas and
        then just leave the gray areas as gray areas.
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <p>
                <em>Well-defined rules:</em> The rules are written in a way that makes it absolutely clear how to play
                the game. Everyone who carefully reads and follows the rules will end up playing the same game.
            </p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>
                <em>Well-defined decision points:</em> The types of games we will be analyzing need to be clear about
                when decisions need to be made and what the possible decisions are at any moment. A simple way to think
                about this is that at any point in the game, it makes sense to ask the questions "Whose turn is it?" and
                "What are the valid moves?"
            </p>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>
                <em>Well-defined outcomes:</em> After a decision has been made, it must be clear what happens next, and
                it must be the same thing would happen to any other player that makes the same decision in an identical
                situation. This part of the definition is a bit tricky to interpret, and leaves a little bit of room
                for ambiguity. One thing we want to avoid is the outcome being dependent upon the individual and not the
                structure of the game. For example, in a game like darts, the outcome of a throw is not a random event
                like throwing a die. The outcome is not driven by the rules of the game, but by the skill of the
                individual, which means that the outcomes are not well-defined.
            </p>
        </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
        With this in place we can look at a number of games and see whether they meet our definition. Again, things that
        fall outside of the definition can still be games in the general sense. It's just that they aren't the types of
        games we will be analyzing.
    </p>
    <ul>
        <li>
            <p>Chess:</p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    Well-defined rules: There is a clear set of rules for how every piece moves and how they interact
                    with each other. There are a few special moves (castling and en passant) that violate the basic
                    pattern of movement, but these special situations are clearly laid out in an unambiguous manner.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined decision points: This is a two=player game where the players take turns, and there is a
                    clear set of valid moves for each turn.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined outcomes: When a piece is moved to a new position, the game's structure defines the
                    outcome.
                </li>
                <li>
                    From this, we conclude that chess is a gmae.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>
                Monopoly:
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    Well-defined rules: The game comes with instructions that clearly describe how the game is to be
                    played. However, a lot of people play with various "house rules" (such as collecting money on Free
                    Parking) that deviate from the official rules. As long as everyone can understand and agree with how
                    the rule is meant to be implemented, it continues to have well-defined rules. (On a technical note,
                    we would probably say that they are playing a variant of Monopoly instead of just Monopoly.)
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined decision points: If we ignore the auction phase of the game, the game proceeds in an
                    organized manner, with players taking their turns in a specific order, and having a clear set of
                    options in front of them at any moment. But the existence of the auction potentially violates this.
                    If the auction requires players to bid with no specific order (first to call out a number owns the
                    bid), the auction phase lacks clear decision points. If the auction is run by taking turns bidding,
                    then there are clear decision points.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined outcomes: When a player lands on a space, there is a clear outcome based on the rules
                    of the game.
                </li>
                <li>
                    From this, we conclude that Monopoly is a gmae if the auction is run in a particular manner.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </li>
        <li>
            <p>
                Sudoku: This one is a bit tricky. In this course, we will consider certain types of logic puzzles to be
                games, so we have to be a little bit flexible in how we interpret the conditions.
            </p>
            <ul>
                <li>
                    Well-defined rules: The game is played by a person writing numbers into the squares of the puzzle.
                    There is a clear set of rules for what those numbers could be.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined decision points: The decision points for a Sudoku are when the player commits a certain
                    value to a certain position on the grid. In this sense, the game is played by a clear sequence of
                    moves as the player slowly fills out the grid.
                </li>
                <li>
                    Well-defined outcomes: A particular entry may be valid or invalid, depending on whether the player
                    has made a mistake. The player's lack of knowledge of their move is part of the game. As the grid
                    is filled out more completely, the player "loses" if they find that they cannot legally write a
                    digit into some position of the grid. But the player "wins" if they fill out the entire grid and all
                    the rules are satisfied.
                </li>
                <li>
                    From this, we can see that a Sudoku can be considered to be a game for this course. Whether one
                    ultimately decides to consider puzzles as games is a decision that is left to the individual.
                </li>
            </ul>
        </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
        As we explore the topic more deeply, we will develop specific tools for analyze games, and this will bring
        these ideas more clearly into focus.
    </p>

    <worksheet xml:id="game-intro-wksht">
		<title>Exercises</title>
		<exercisegroup>
            <title>The Definition of a Game</title>
            <p>
                For each of the following activities, determine whether it is a game based on our definition. If it is not
                a game, describe which of the properties it violates. Note that some of these may be debatable. Discussion
                about disagreements with others is encouraged.
            </p>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Checkers
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Billiards
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Poker
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    A slot machine
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Scrabble
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    A game of tag
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Jigsaw puzzles
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Fortnight
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Make a list of 3-5 games (in the casual sense) that you've played in your life. Which of them would be
                    classified as a game (in the formal sense of this class)?
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Try to identify a game that is in a gray area based on the definition provided. Which of the three
                    conditions leads to an unclear result? Explain your answer.
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </worksheet>


</section>