<section xml:id="PN-Position">
    <title>P-Positions and N-Positions</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn what P-positions and N-positions are.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn how the knowledge of P-positions and N-positions improves your strategic play.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <observation>
        Consider the following statements:
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    I try to make good decisions.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    I try to avoid bad decisions.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
        Do you think these are the same idea? Why or why not?
    </observation>

    <p>
        We are going to start off this section by introducing some vocabulary to describe game states.
    </p>
    <definition xml:id="def-PN-Position">
        <title>P-Position and N-Position</title>
        <idx><h>N-Position</h></idx>
        <idx><h>P-Position</h></idx>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A <term>P-position</term> in a game is a game state where the player who just played (the previous
                player) can guarantee a win if they make the right decisions. An <term>N-position</term> in a game is a
                game state where the next player to play can guarantee a win if they make the right decisions.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </definition>
    <p>
        In our analysis of 15-Countdown, we saw that if there are one, two, or three tokens and it's your turn, you
        should just take all of them and win. Since the next player to play has a guaranteed win (if they make the right
        decisions), this is an N-position.
    </p>
    <p>
        We also saw that if there are four tokens remaining and it's your turn, that there's nothing you can do to stop
        your opponent from winning. If you take one, they will take three and win. If you take two, they will take two
        and win. If you take three, they will take one and win. So if your opponent doesn't make any mistakes, they're
        going to win. This means the game is in a P-position since the previous player who played has the guaranteed
        win. Also, notice that the game state of zero tokens is also P-position because the previous player has already
        won the game, and so they are guaranteed the win.
    </p>
    <p>
        We can include the labels of P and N in our game trees. Here is how it will look for the endgame of
        15-Countdown.
    </p>
	<image xml:id="PN-Position-4-labeled" width="50%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
                \foreach \x in {0,1,...,4}
                    \draw (-\x,0) node[circle, draw] (\x) {\small \x};
    
                \draw[-latex] (4) to (3);
                \draw[-latex] (3) to (2);
                \draw[-latex] (2) to (1);
                \draw[-latex] (1) to (0);
            
                \draw[-latex] (4) to[out=35, in=145] (2);
                \draw[-latex] (3) to[out=35, in=145] (1);
                \draw[-latex] (2) to[out=35, in=145] (0);
            
                \draw[-latex] (4) to[out=45, in=135] (1);
                \draw[-latex] (3) to[out=45, in=135] (0);            

                \draw (-4,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {P};
                \draw (-3,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw (-2,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw (-1,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw (0,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {P};
            \end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
    <p>
        We want to take a moment and think about how these positions interact with each other. Consider the following
        game tree. The current game state is denoted with an X, and the other nodes are labeled as either a P-position
        or an N-position.
    </p>
	<image xml:id="PN-Position-decision" width="50%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
                \draw (0,0) node[circle, draw] (0) {\small X};
                \draw (-2,-1.5) node[circle, draw] (1) {\small N};
                \draw (-1,-1.5) node[circle, draw] (2) {\small N};
                \draw (0,-1.5) node[circle, draw] (3) {\small P};
                \draw (1,-1.5) node[circle, draw] (4) {\small N};
                \draw (2,-1.5) node[circle, draw] (5) {\small P};
            
                \draw[-latex] (0) to (1);
                \draw[-latex] (0) to (2);
                \draw[-latex] (0) to (3);
                \draw[-latex] (0) to (4);
                \draw[-latex] (0) to (5);
            \end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
    <p>
        Let's say that it's your turn. How would you want to play? All we need to do is think about the meaning of the
        positions. Remember that P-position is a gamestate where the previous player can guarantee a win. Since it's
        currently your turn, you would want to end your turn on a P-position because that would make you the previous
        player and the person who is on a path to victory. In theory, it makes no difference which P-position we move to
        because both of them have a guaranteed win. However, in practice there might be situations where the strategy
        may be more complicated in one position than the other, and that might lead you to favor the one that's simpler
        so that you avoid making mistakes.
    </p>
    <p>
        This analysis shows us something very important and useful about our decisions. If it is our turn to make a
        move, then we should be looking to move the game to a P-position. In fact, if you are able to make a move from
        the current position to a P-position, then that would make the current position a N-position since the next
        player (you) are able to make a move that guarantees a win.
    </p>
    <p>
        If we are unable to move the game to a P-position, then all the edges must point to N-positions. This means that
        no matter what move you make, you'll leave the game in a position where your opponent has a move that can
        guarantee a win. Since we are analyzing two-player games, your opponent is the previous player, and they have
        the winning move, so that makes this a P-position.
    </p>
    <p>
        These two observations give us our first theorem. (A theorem is a fancy mathematical term for a result that we
        know is true.)
    </p>
    <theorem xml:id="thm-PN-positions">
        <title>Characterizing P-Positions and N-Positions</title>
        <statement>
            <p>
                A node in a game tree is an N-position if one of the edges points to a P-position. If there are no edges
                that point from a particular node to an P-position (that is, all of the edges point to N-positions),
                then that node must be an P-position.
            </p>
        </statement>
    </theorem>
    <p>
        We can confirm this result by looking at the 15-Countdown endgame tree. If we look at the N-positions, we can
        see that each of them has an edge that points to a P-position. And if we look at the P-positions, we can see
        that all the edges point to N-positions, if there even any edges at all.
    </p>
    <p>
        In the previous section, there were some exercises that had you analyze 15-Countdown when there are 5 and 6
        tokens remaining. You should have found that if there are 5 tokens, the optimal play is to take one token so
        that there would be 4 remaining. And if there are 6 tokens, then you should take two. Both of these analyses
        reflect the idea that you're trying to move the game to a P-position.
    </p>
    <p>
        Let's do a more methodical analysis for 7 tokens. We know that the available moves are to bring the total number
        of tokens to 6, 5, or 4. We saw that both 6 tokens and 5 tokens are N-positions, and we know from earlier that 4
        tokens is a P-position. Since there is a pathway to a P-position, the 7 token position is an N-position and the
        winning move is to remove three tokens to leave 4. (In the image below, the bad moves have been grayed out for
        emphasis.)
    </p>
	<image xml:id="PN-Position-7-labeled" width="50%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
                \draw (0,0) node[circle, draw] (7) {\small 7};
                \draw[gray] (1,0) node[circle, draw] (6) {\small 6};
                \draw[gray] (2,0) node[circle, draw] (5) {\small 5};
                \draw (3,0) node[circle, draw] (4) {\small 4};
    
                \draw[gray, -latex] (7) to (6);
                \draw[gray, -latex] (7) to[out=35, in=145] (5);
                \draw[-latex] (7) to[out=45, in=135] (4);

                \draw[gray] (1,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw[gray] (2,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw (3,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {P};
            \end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
    <p>
        Now we will analyze the 8 token scenario. We can see that the 7, 6, and 5 scenarios are all N-positions. This
        means that when there are 8 tokens remaining, there are no winning moves. Since there are no winning moves, the
        position is not an N-position (the next player cannot win) and so it is a P-position.
    </p>
	<image xml:id="PN-Position-8-labeled" width="50%">
		<latex-image>
			\begin{tikzpicture}
                \draw (0,0) node[circle, draw] (8) {\small 8};
                \draw[gray] (1,0) node[circle, draw] (7) {\small 7};
                \draw[gray] (2,0) node[circle, draw] (6) {\small 6};
                \draw[gray] (3,0) node[circle, draw] (5) {\small 5};
    
                \draw[gray, -latex] (8) to (7);
                \draw[gray, -latex] (8) to[out=35, in=145] (6);
                \draw[gray, -latex] (8) to[out=45, in=135] (5);

                \draw[gray] (1,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw[gray] (2,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
                \draw[gray] (3,-0.75) node[anchor=center] {N};
            \end{tikzpicture} 
		</latex-image>
	</image>
    <p>
        In fact, we can push this idea further to analyze the entire game! The key is that we are working backwards,
        starting from the end of the game and moving towards the beginning. The reason this is helpful is because as we
        analyze those late game positions, we have more known labels with which to analyze earlier positions.
    </p>

    <worksheet xml:id="PN-Position-wksht">
		<title>Exercises</title>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>15-Countdown</title>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Complete the analysis of 15-Countdown by continuing to work backwards. Is the initial position a 
                    P-position or an N-position? Does that mean that you would want to go first or second? Explain your
                    reasoning.
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Make a list of the P-positions you found in your analysis. What is the pattern?
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    It's one thing to say that X is the right move because that's what the game tree says is the right
                    move, and it's another to be able to describe the strategy based on logic or reasoning applied to
                    the game itself. Can you explain the pattern for winning plays while only referring to the game
                    structures and not the game tree?
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>The Genearlized Countdown Game</title>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Choose your own Generalized Countdown game and determine all of the P-positions and N-positions.
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    What patterns (if any) do you observe in the winning moves of this game?
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>Exploring Nim</title>
            <p> 
                For each of the problems in this section, assume you're playing a game of Nim where you start with three
                heaps whose sizes are 4, 2, and 1.
            </p>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Identify all of the P-positions and N-positions.
                </p>
            </exercise>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    What patterns (if any) do you observe in the winning moves of this game? (Note: You may find
                    patterns that only apply to some of the winning moves. Feel free to present those as an answer to
                    this question.)
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </worksheet>

</section>