<section xml:id="sudoku-intro">
    <title>Introduction to Sudoku</title>

    <objectives>
        <ul>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn how to play Sudoku.
                </p>
            </li>
            <li>
                <p>
                    You will learn the basic strategies for placing numbers in the grid without guessing.
                </p>
            </li>
        </ul>
    </objectives>

    <observation>
        What is your experience with logic puzzles?
    </observation>

    <p>
        Sudoku is a classic pen-and-paper puzzle. (A pen-and-paper puzzle is a puzzle that can be given to you on
        paper and solved using just a pen and your brain.) If you look around, you will be able to find all sorts of
        puzzle books that contain them, as well as dozens of websites or apps that let you access gigantic libraries
        of puzzles. 
    </p>
    <p>
        The standard Sudoku grid is a 9x9 square grid that has been broken up into 9 3x3 boxes. A valid Sudoku grid is
        one in which every square in the grid is filled with one of the digits from 1 to 9 subject to the condition that
        each digit appears in every row, column, and box exactly once. The diagram below shows a valid Sudoku grid.
    </p>
    <image xml:id="sudoku-demo-1" width="75%">
        <latex-image>
            \begin{tikzpicture}[scale=0.5]
                \draw (0,0) grid (9,9);
                \foreach \x in {0,3,6} {
                    \foreach \y in {0,3,6} {
                        \draw[thick] (\x, \y) rectangle (\x + 3, \y + 3);
                    }
                }
            \end{tikzpicture}
        </latex-image>
    </image>
    <p>
        A typical puzzle starts with only some of the squares filled with digits, and it is up to the player to fill in
        the remaining digits to get a valid Sudoku grid. A well-constructed puzzle will lead to the ability to complete
        the grid using logic and without guessing. Solving the puzzle by guessing somewhat defeats the purpose of the
        puzzle, which is the practice and experience of reasoning and pattern-recognition to reap the reward of a sense
        of accomplishment.
    </p>
    <p>
        Even though the standard Sudoku is completed using numbers, the numbers themselves do not play a role in the
        puzzle. They are just a collection of distinct symbols. For example, a 
    </p>


    <worksheet xml:id="sudoku-intro-wksht">
		<title>Exercises</title>
        <exercisegroup>
            <title>TITLE</title>
            <p>
                TEXT
            </p>
            <exercise>
                <p>
                    Exercise
                </p>
            </exercise>
        </exercisegroup>
    </worksheet>

</section>